明 嘉靖年间
During the reign of Ming Emperor Jiajing (1522-1567)
由于朝廷海禁地方官府腐败沿海倭寇蜂起
Japanese pirates raided the coastlines of China because of the sea ban.
其中被认为乃倭寇之首的
The chief of these Japanese pirates
却是一个安徽人王直屡次进犯沿海
was actually a Han Chinese man called Wang Zhi.
嘉靖三十六年
In 1557,
浙江总督胡宗宪说服王直投诚
The Zhejiang commander led Wang
助除倭寇之患
to turn against the pirates.
怎料王直随即被杭州竭巡按王本固收押
But Wang was subsequently imprisoned by the Governor of Hangzhou.
倭寇不降反四处生事攻击浙江沿海
So the pirates continued to raid the coastal areas of Zhejiang.
此时王直之义子毛海峰
Wang's godson Mao Haifeng
与一支上千人的倭寇部队
and over 1,000 pirates
占据了浙江岑港
occupied Cengang
大量自沿海抢来的各种物资集结于此
with the loot pillaged from the coast.
明军在俞大猷指挥下围攻了五个多月
The army under Commander Yu Dayou besieged them for 5 months.
浙江总兵  俞大猷
Yu Dayou Garrison Commander of Zhejiang"
荡       寇       风       云
毛     劲     松     封     装
Mao Jinsong encapsulation
冲呀
Charge!
一起 开炮
Fire!
冲呀
Charge!
将军
General!
将军 你没事吧
Are you alright?
将军 快要顶不住了
We can't hold them off!
撤吧
We should fall back.
撤退
Retreat!
大人
Sir!
他们就这样傻傻的
Like fools,
每次按着同一时辰来攻我们呢
they launch their attacks at the same hour each time.
铁炮队 收队
Guns Unit dismissed!
按时早饭
They eat on time,
按时冲锋 按时败退
attack and retreat on time.
明军真有纪律呀
The Ming troops have such discipline!
大人
Sir!
部队们见一直都是浪人在领功
The ronins get all the credit.
士兵们不会觉得没趣吗
Won't the soldiers feel snubbed?
谢谢
Thank you.
对付这些明军
The ronins are sufficient
浪人就够了
to take on the Ming troops.
既然明军如此不济
If these troops are so pathetic,
将军为何不进攻内地
why didn't you invade the inland
胁迫朝廷放我义父
and force the Ming Court to release my godfather?
将军
General,
忘了松蒲大人的话了
have you forgotten what Lord Matsura said?
海峰兄
Haifeng,
不用提醒我
no need to remind me.
五峰大人对松蒲藩的贡献 我们都很清楚
We're aware of Master Wufeng's (Wang Zhi) contribution to the Matsura clan.
但 松蒲大人说过这里的所有行动
But Lord Matsura made it clear
不能以他的名义进行
we're not acting on his behalf.
我们是倭寇 不是松蒲军
We're wokou.
我们是贼
We are pirates,
领头的是五峰大人
under the command of Master Wufeng.
当六十个浪人
If 60 ronins
可以直达南京城下捣乱明军时
can reach Nanjing and defeat the Ming troops,
我们一千部队
we have a regiment of 1,000 men,
为何只守不攻
why can't we take the offensive?
孙子用兵之法
According to the Art of War,
十则围之五则攻之
encircle when we outnumber the enemy 10 to 1
明军以十倍于我军的军队围攻我
and attack when it's 5 to 1.
我们可以守住
We only managed to hold them off
是倚仗地利天险
because we have the benefit of a natural barrier.
我一千军队一旦没有了地利
Without that edge,
也一样会输
we will lose just the same.
我们会像那60个浪人一样结束
We will end up like those 60 ronins.
大人
Sir!
大人太高估明国的军队了
You have overestimated the Ming troops.
光是南方就有驻军二十万
They have 200,000 men stationed in the south
对手是明国将军俞大猷
under the command of Yu Dayou.
明国的军队贪生怕死朝廷官员贪污腐败
Ming troops are cowards and Court officials are corrupted.
多来几个俞大猷又有什么用
A few more like Yu Dayou means nothing.
最近呢
Recently,
有一个文武双全叫戚继光的将军出现
a general named Qi Jiguang showed up
他带领明军连战连胜
and led the Ming troops in winning several battles.
戚继光
Qi Jiguang?
在干什么
What are they doing?
这班畜牲
Bastards!
由得他们吧
Leave them alone.
为什么
Why?
老师
Sensei
我们是武士却要跟这些流氓一起作战
why should samurais fight alongside ronins
还要看着他们胡作非为
and put up with their atrocious behavior?
这只是各取所需
To each his own.
我们漂洋过海来到这里
We came from across the ocean
是要为大名取得财富
to help the Daimyo build his fortune
购买火枪好让主公强大起来
and to buy firearms to make him powerful.
而他们要的是
They came here
女人钱财
for women and money.
他们的行径不合武士仁义
Their behavior is unworthy of a samurai.
但也得满足他们
But we must keep them happy
这样他们才会卖命的
so they will risk their lives for us.
少主 你只要记住
You must remember
我们能在此赚钱买武器
we're here to make money and buy weapons
只是为了统一天下
in order Japan can rule the world.
其他的事情都不重要
Nothing else matters.
要打败明国
To defeat the Ming Court,
不能只谈仁义也要有战略
benevolence is not enough. We also need strategy.
待山川少主你成了大名之后
When you become the Daimyo, Master Yamagawa,
到时候再多谈仁义吧
you can be more benevolent.
万一被明国知道是我们松蒲出兵
If the Ming Court found out we're from the Matsura Army,
会让松蒲藩陷于危险
it will endanger the Matsura clan.
我们是倭寇
We're pirates,
穷凶极恶的倭寇
savage pirates.
少主你懂吗
Do you understand?
俞将军
General Yu!
胡大人
Commander Hu!
你受伤了
You're injured!
小伤而已
It's nothing.
我正准备天黑之前再冲锋
I intend to launch another attack before dark.
"Hu Zongxian Supreme Commander of Zhejiang"
像这样的冲锋有用吗
What's the use?
俞将军
General Yu!
宁绍台参将戚继光
I'm Assistant Regional Military Commissioner Qi Jiguang.
你就是戚继光
So you're Qi Jiguang.
你说我冲锋没用
If you think my plan doesn't work,
那你有什么有用的方法
you have a better idea?
尚无方法
Not yet.
不过像俞将军这样冲锋
You've been doing this
也有好几个月了吧
for several months, right?
俞将军
General Yu,
京中再三催促
the Imperial Court is getting impatient.
离一月破敌之日只有二十天
You have 20 days left of your one-month deadline.
所以呢
That's why
我打算让元敬训练的新军试一试
I intend to let Jiguang give it a try with his New Army.
元敬的新军
They have wiped out pirates
已经接连在浙西剿灭了三路贼兵
in western Zhejiang in 3 successive battles.
俞将军
General Yu,
你已经久攻了好几个月了吧
you have been fighting for months.
人马疲乏
You must be exhausted.
而且你的属下多以水师为主
Besides, most of your men are trained at sea...
属下遵从命令就是
I will follow your orders.
胡大人不必解释
There's no need to explain.
"Lu Tong Second Commander of Zhejiang"
胡大人只是想让俞将军稍事休息而已
Commander Hu only wants you to rest up.
卢将军 我们走吧
Let's go, General Lu!
喝酒去
Let's go for a drink.
好 请
Sure! After you...
元敬
Jiguang,
先锋的重任就交给你
I'm making you the vanguard.
戚继光必全力以赴
I'll do my best.
"A few months ago"
"Longshang, Cixi"
谁叫你开炮
Who asked you to open fire?
攻呀
Charge!
谁给跑 给我站住
Who's running away? Stop!
把敌人的头拿回来
Bring me their heads.
大家冲呀
Charge!
不要后退
Don't back off!
危险 退后
Watch out! Fall back!
撤退
Retreat!
"Hu Zongxian Residence"
数量核示清楚
Count them carefully!
胡大人
Commander!
元敬你来了
Jiguang,
来来来
come here
你们调兵遣将
You deploy the troops,
我呢只懂调钱调财
I deploy the money.
这浙江如今是什么都缺呀
Zhejiang is short of supplies right now.
坐吧
Have a seat.
龙山所雁门岭之役
At the battle of Yanmen Ridge,
我们以数倍倭寇的兵力
we outnumbered the pirates,
只和他们打个平手
but we only managed a tie.
怎么还敢报功呢
We dared not report a victory.
不曲道以媚时
Never violate the rules of life to suit the time.
不诡行以邀名
Never commit treachery to attain fame.
这个道理世人皆懂
It is easier said than done.
可我却做不到
I, for one, cannot do it.
你可知道
Do you know
此时此刻有多少双眼睛在盯着我们吗
all eyes are on us right now?
我们如今只能赢 不能输
We can't afford to lose.
输了 朝廷震动天下权变
A defeat will shake the Imperial Court to its core.
所以这一战
This is a battle
你只能赢
you must win.
你三箭定胜负
The three arrows you shot
已成军中美颂
became a legend in the Army.
大家都指 能在你手下作战
Everyone hopes to fight under your command.
心中会有安稳之心呀
They feel safe.
败就败在求安稳之心呀
But this is also our handicap.
大人
Commander,
当兵的哪有求安稳的
soldiers should not expect to be safe.
大人 我请许重组新军
Please allow me to set up a new army.
请大人批许
I need your approval.
杀贼方是当务之急
Fighting the pirates is your top priority.
怎么能去练兵呢
You have no time to train soldiers.
你专心杀敌就好了
Concentrate on taking out the enemies.
可是他们见到倭寇就跑
The sight of pirates make them flee.
仗还没打就已经败了
The battle is lost before it began.
大人你说这仗怎么打
How can we fight like that?
有你在 大家一定会变的
They can change with you in command.
这正是我从山东把你请过来的目的
This is why I brought you from Shandong.
要你 杀敌邀功
I need you to wipe out the pirates.
我们可以杀敌 练兵两不担误同时进行
I can kill pirates and train soldiers at the same time.
练新兵 练新兵 元敬
Train soldiers...
浙江兵怕倭寇
Zhejiang soldiers are scared of pirates.
已经是个定局了 练不了的
That's a fact. What more can you do?
大人
Commander,
十室之邑必有忠信
you can find someone faithful even in a town with 10 houses.
堂堂全浙 岂无材勇
There must be someone courageous in Zhejiang.
况且由我来自行训练
If I'm in charge of the training,
更可以省掉不少请客兵的军费
you can save the money on hiring Guest Troops.
好呀
Very well!
好呀 元敬
Very well, Jiguang.
难得你愿意费神再去训练新军
If you take the trouble to train a new army,
我怎么能不支持呢
I must show my support.
只是雁门岭一役
About the battle of Yanmen Ridge,
我必须要报军功
we must report this extraordinary feat
全歼倭寇 就这么定了
of wiping out the pirates.
上 上
Go!
哥
Jiguang!
我们日日闹了好几天了
We have been doing this for days.
什么时候打呀？
When are we going to fight?
你有方法攻上去吗
You have a better plan?
这有什么办法 冲呀
What plan? Just charge ahead!
将军每天来
The General comes here every day
就想破敌之法
trying to think of a plan.
不攻不打
We don't attack or fight,
不就让敌人松懈嘛
because we want the enemy to let their guard down.
楼楠 你又猜到我在想什么了
Lou Nan, you can always read my mind.
这太可怕了
That's too scary!
回去吧
Let's go back.
明军又不攻进来了
The Ming Army did not launch an attack.
是不敢战吗
Are they afraid to fight?
三十不到已被奉为名将
He made a name for himself before he turned 30.
这人是个奇才
Don't lower your guard.
别掉以轻心
This man is a genius.
回营休息 收起将旗
Let's return to camp and take down the banners.
是
Aye!
将军
General!
开始下雨了
It's raining!
哥
Jiguang,
这仗什么都准备好了
everything is ready.
现在下着雨
Shouldn't we
我们不就是应该趁着下雨夜袭嘛？
launch the attack in the rain?
趁着下雨夜袭
In the rain?
是呀
Yes!
你能想得出来
If you can think of it,
倭寇也能想得到
so can the pirates.
去休息吧
Go get some rest.
这说是休息
You should
不是应该回军营休息吗 哥
return to camp.
行行行 休息休息
Alright... I'll get some rest.
你哥向来以奇兵取胜
Your brother is known to take his enemies by surprise.
等吧
Let's wait!
听命
Listen up...
原地休息
get some rest!
小心明军趁着下雨夜袭
Beware of an attack in the rain at night.
大家提高警觉
Be vigilant!
听清楚没有 啊
Did you hear me?
真多想法
What a pain!
好吧
Very well!
别吵了 在怕什么
What are you afraid of?
还给你
Here...
安心吧 我没碰过她
Relax! I didn't lay a hand on her!
我是武士
I'm a samurai,
跟你们不一样
unlike the lot of you.
木幡 喝酒
Drink up, Kohata!
都睡着了
They're asleep.
太好了
Excellent
通知俞将军 只要一听到炮声
Tell General Yu to meet me in the mountain
就上山和我们会合
when he hears the cannon.
把大家叫醒 马上出发
Wake up the troops, we're moving out.
小声点
Keep it down!
什么事
What's going on?
拉…
Pull...
突袭 被突袭了
A raid! We've been attacked!
上呀
Charge!
冲
go
糟了
We're in trouble!
攻呀
Run!
Charge!
跟我走 来
Follow me!
我不去
I'm not going!
给我追
After them!
第一部队 出击
Unit 1, charge!
出发
Let's move out!
大人
Sir!
明军已突破我们的防线
The Ming Army broke through our line of defense.
那么快
Already?
那个将军果然厉害
That general is formidable indeed.
老师
Sensei,
我们过去帮忙吧
let's go give them a hand.
已攻上了寨门就守不住了
They're at the front gate. We can't hold them back.
我们不会输给明军
We won't let them beat us.
明国是一头大象 不能硬碰的
The Ming Dynasty is like an elephant; you can't take it head on.
只打必胜的 不打平手的
I want a win, not a tie.
即使打胜但有损伤我也不愿意
But not a win at the expense of casualties.
还是退吧
We should retreat.
大人 退吗
Are you sure?
谁愿意殿后
Who's willing to bring up the rear?
当然是我
Me, of course!
拜托你
Thank you!
是
Yes!
准备收拾行装
Let's pack up and go!
明白
Aye!
去吧
Go!
撤退
Retreat!
撤退吧
Come on!
少主
Master Yamagawa,
可以帮我忙吗
can you give me a hand?
我很乐意
My pleasure.
撤退 撤退
Retreat!
这边走
This way!
你们要走
You must leave.
不舍得也要快点撤退
We must go even if you don't want to.
俞将军
General Yu!
请进
Please come in.
佩服了
Impressive!
I'm impressed!
楼楠
Lou Nan!
将军
General!
怎么回事
What is it?
贼兵已经走了
The pirates are gone.
地上很多碎银
They left behind scraps of silver.
将士们都在四处搜银
The soldiers are busy picking them up.
哥 这村民要见你
Jiguang, this villager wants to see you.
将军 将军
General...
起来说话
Please get UP!
将军 还有很多村民被锁在旧房里面
Other villagers are still locked up.
将军你快去救救他们吧 将军
Please rescue them quickly, General.
带我去
Take me there!
就在这
Over here!
哥
Jiguang!
戚将军来救我们了
General Qi is hereto save us.
大家快出来 快出
Come out, all of you!
戚将军来救我们了
General Qi is hereto save us.
快出来
Come out!
谢谢将军
Thank you, General Qi!
好好好 起来吧
Please get UP!
抓住戚继光
Grab Qi!
杀
Kill!
撤呀
Let's go!
蹲下
Get down!
准备好
Ready!
开炮
Fire!
哥
Jiguang!
救人 快救人
Get them out! Hurry!
哥
Jiguang!
救人 快
Help them...
哥
Jiguang!
你没事吧 哥
Are you alright?
我没事
I'm fine.
救人
Help them...
贼兵当中
Among the pirates,
大部份都是因为海禁
majority of them were Han Chinese dispossessed by the sea ban
而投靠王直的汉人
and sought refuge with Wang Zhi.
你是说我们打的不是倭寇
You're saying they are not Japanese?
也有浪人
They include Japanese ronins.
但最有战斗力的
But those with genuine combat prowess
而是一群配备精良的倭兵
are well equipped Japanese soldiers.
倭兵
Japanese soldiers?
我们就是碰到他们
That's who we're dealing with.
很少见
They're rare.
将军 胡大人来了
General, Commander Hu is here.
又来了
Again?
恭喜两位将军
Congratulations,
胡大人带来了上好的黄酒
Commander Hu brought the best yellow wine
跟大家庆祝一下
to celebrate with you.
胡大人为何带锦衣卫进来
Why did you bring the Imperial Secret Service with you?
侍中罗嘉宾几个人正要上书弹劾你
Luo Jiabin and his lot intend to impeach you
说你放走倭寇
for letting the pirates get away.
指你通敌
They said you colluded with them.
我没通敌
I did not!
我当然心里清楚了
I know.
我已经上报朝廷报捷了
I already reported your victory.
在朝廷尚未收到捷报之前
But before my report reaches the Court,
你先要留在家里
you are to stay home
听候发落
pending your sentence.
俞将军
General Yu,
抱歉了
I'm sorry!
没问题
No problem!
我会尽力周旋的
I will do my best to intercede.
不要只抓俞将军
Don't just arrest General Yu.
要抓两个一起抓
Put me under arrest as well.
朝廷有命
I have my orders.
俞将军出师不利
General Yu failed his expedition
纵寇南逃
and allowed the pirates to flee to the South.
需暂时交锦衣卫收押
The Imperial Secret Service will take him into custody.
俞将军 得罪了 请
Pardon us, General! This way.
明白
I understand.
俞将军
General Yu...
没事的
I'll be fine.
这不是我能决定的
It wasn't my decision to make.
当官当得这么委屈
This is so unfair.
那就不要当了
You should quit.
房子多太 俸禄多少
Tiny house, small salary...
我又不稀罕
Who cares?
那姓胡的声名狼藉
Hu Zongxian is notorious.
你在他手下
Working for him,
败是坏事 成也可能是坏事
win or lose, you're doomed.
我这妇人之见
This is just my humble opinion.
听还是不听
Whether or not you want to listen,
随你
it's up to you.
夫人讲的每一句话都有道理
You make perfect sense.
可是倭寇大敌当前
But the enemy is at the gate,
我又怎能不理
I can't just walk away.
那就天下大事
It's a state matter;
可是只有你一个人可担当
you can't do this alone.
不是还心中郁闷吗？
I thought you're depressed.
怎么不规矩起来了
Why this disorderly behavior?
我怎么不规矩呢
What do you mean?
夫妻行周公之礼
Sexual intercourse between husband and wife
是天经地义之事
is the most natural and proper thing to do.
又想拿礼法压我吗
Don't throw the book in my face again.
我哪敢
I wouldn't dare.
有什么不敢的
Of course you would.
你不是天下无敌吗
You're invincible.
夫人才是真正的天下无敌
You're the invincible one.
我们的盾挡不住呀
Our shields are not tough enough.
再想想办法
We'll think of something.
这就是毛海峰的倭刀
This is Mao Haifeng's sword.
哥
Here...
这刀给你当配刀吧
You can use this.
那可不行
Absolutely not!
堂堂大明将军拿一把倭刀
A Ming general using a Japanese sword
岂不长了别人的威风
is bad for morale.
不过这刀倒是挺锋利的
No doubt this is a good sword.
是啊 想不到如此锐利
I'm surprised it's such a trenchant sword.
应该跟我们的打造方法不一样
I think it's made differently from ours.
继美
Jimei!
你琢磨琢磨
Study it carefully,
看看这刀是怎样锻成的
and find out how it's forged.
好
Sure!
将军
General!
戚将军
General Qi!
胡大人刚收到了朝廷公文
Commander Hu just received Court documents
将军于舟山岑港破敌立功
about your victory at Cengang.
官复原职
You have been reinstated.
好呀
Good!
那俞大猷将军呢
What about General Yu?
还没有俞将军复职的消息
There has been no word.
来
Come!
俞将军
General Yu!
戚将军 卢将军
General Qi! General Lu!
你们来得正好
I'm glad you're here.
这就是我跟你们说
This is General Qi Jiguang,
大破岑港贼兵的戚继光
who commanded the decisive victory at Cengang.
久仰久仰
We have heard so much about you.
三位将军慢用
Enjoy!
都已经官复原职了
You have been reinstated.
还有什么忧心的
What are you worried about?
没想到
I didn't expect
俞将军坐牢也能坐得这么轻松
you'd be so relaxed in jail.
这些年来
Over the years,
在战场上牺牲的兄弟你知道有多少
have you any idea how many men were lost in battle?
我不过在这里等候发落
I'm just waiting for my sentence.
还有一些兄弟可以切磋武功
I can still practice with my men.
有什么可怨呢
What's there to complain about?
俞将军抗倭多年
You have fought the pirates for years
功劳不少
and earned great merit.
难道不觉得委屈吗
Don't you feel aggrieved?
我战倭多年
Yes, I fought pirates for years.
倭患除了吗
Have they been wiped out?
我惭愧呀
I feel ashamed.
凭什么委屈
I have no right to feel aggrieved.
我们在前线以血奋战
We shed our blood on the frontline
而那些昏官却在背后说三道四
while those fatuous officials badmouth us behind our backs,
还把责任推到您身上
and try to pin the blame on you.
您不觉得不安吗？
You don't find that unsettling?
你是说胡大人
You mean Commander Hu?
他为官难啊
It hasn't been easy for him.
若不是胡大人和徐渭大人
Commander Hu and Xu Wei
他们用各种方法保住俞某
did their best to cover up for me.
可能俞某已经跟张经大人一样身首异处了
Or else I would have been beheaded like Zhang Jing.
胡宗宪和严嵩的干儿子赵文华一伙
Hu Zongxian colluded with Yan Song's godson Zhao Wenhua
为他们出谋划策
and did their bidding.
不仅取代了张经大人
He replaced Commander Zhang Jing
更害死了他
and had him executed.
难道是假的吗
None of that is true?
胡大人不跟赵文华周旋
If Commander Hu didn't kiss up to Zhao Wenhua,
你我人头能保
you and I are probably dead by now.
我们何来军饷
Where do you think the army provisions came from?
何来战倭的机会
We'd never get the chance to fight pirates.
胡大人争取的
He bargained for a thankless job
是一个连打胜仗都会被杀头的苦差
that could have him beheaded even if he had won.
你说他这是何苦呢
Why should he bother?
我这命 原来就是胡大人捡回来的
Commander Hu saved my life.
无憾了
I have no complaints.
我们习武之人
As a martial artist,
问心无愧便是了
I'm satisfied as long as I have a clear conscience.
能有你来接这担子
I'm also pleased
我欣慰
that you will now take over this burden.
来 喝一杯
Here... have a drink with me.
胡大人会尽力让我出去的
Commander Hu will get me out.
俞大哥
Brother Yu,
小弟想向您问一件事
can I ask you something?
什么
What?
早闻大哥的棍法
I was told your skill with the staff
威震少林独步天下
is outstanding in Shaolin and unmatched in the world.
上次在岑港
I had a glimpse of it
有幸得以一见
last time in Cengang,
今日想再次请教
I'd like to take another look.
好
Very well!
一寸长 一寸强
An inch longer, an inch stronger.
寸短寸险
An inch shorter, an inch deadlier.
再来
Again!
戚将军 卢将军
General Qi! General Lu!
戚将军
General Qi!
卢将军 戚将军
General Lu! General Qi!
就在这里说
Stay where you are.
得知诸位将军出外勘察
I heard you were going on an inspection tour.
胡大人特派郑某同行协力
Commander Hu sent me to assist you.
请诸位多多指教
I have so much to learn from you.
多多指教
So much indeed.
你这等于来监视我们的吗
Learn from us? You're here to spy on us.
不不不
No...
胡大人指小人懂点笔墨
Because I can read and write,
特意让小人来协助戚将军的
Commander Hu wanted me to assist General Qi.
有劳了
Thank you.
上马了
Let's go!
行了 将军您坐好
Sit tight, General.
好了 可以出发了
We can go now.
嫂子
Sister!
好啊
Excellent
夫人
Wait up...
Wait up!
夫人
Hey...
你怎么了
What's wrong?
怎么了
你去视察地方要几天几夜
You'll be gone for several days.
不带我去也是应该的
Naturally you don't want to bring me along.
谁说的
Says who?
谁说不带你去呀
Who says I'm not bringing you?
那马呢
Then where's my horse?
在备呀
We're getting it ready.
在备
Getting it ready?
夫人 你急什么
What's your hurry?
我怎么舍得把你一个人扔在家里呢
Why would I leave you behind?
我舍得吗
You think I'd want that?
快 快 快了
Hurry...
马备好了
The horse is ready.
哥
Jiguang!
戚夫人 早
Morning, Madam Qi!
卢将军 早
Morning, General Lu!
刚才戚将军正跟我说
General Qi told me just now
等候戚夫人一起上路呢
we're waiting for you.
让卢将军久等了
Sorry to keep you waiting.
夫人
Allow me...
美女
Hey pretty lady!
你别这样
You guys, stop acting like this...
对不起
Sorry!
你们喝多了
You're drunk!
看你的了
Let's see...
不行 看我的呀
No, watch me.
兄弟 喝多了
You're drunk, pal.
我告诉你们
Listen up...
我们可是戚继光的兵
We are Qi Jiguang's troops.
专杀倭寇的
We specialize in killing pirates.
我看 你们就是倭寇
I think you're a pirate.
兄弟们
Brothers...
把他们全给我抓了
take them into custody!
大哥 大哥
Brother...
将军
General!
就是他 就是他打我们
That's him. He beat us up.
闭嘴 都他妈眼瞎了
Shut up! Are you blind?
将军
General,
这些都是你的兵
they're your troops.
他们不是我的兵
They can't be.
用力
Come on...
承让 承让
Thank you...
戚将军 佩服
Impressive, General!
承让 承让
Thank you...
还有没有人想试试
Anyone else?
要不我再来一次
Let me do it again.
算了吧你
Forget it!
戚夫人
Madam Qi?
戚夫人 来来来
Come on...
戚夫人加油
Go for it, Madam Qi...
夫人用力
Harder...
这是什么东西呀
What is that?
这位大哥
Excuse me...
请问这个是怎么用的
what is this for?
这个是脚踩上去
Put your feet inside,
两手扶着
and hold the handle like this.
这个叫什么
What is it called?
这个叫泥马
A mud horse.
在泥中可以行走自如
You can walk in the mud.
泥马
Mud horse?
这个有意思呀
Very interesting.
去体验一下吧 很好玩的
Give it a try. It's a lot fun.
怎么会有这么多人在打架
Why are these people fighting?
是啊
Exactly!
那边有官差呀
The magistrate is over there.
平时就是贪生怕死 你这个混蛋
You're such a coward...
他为什么不管
Why doesn't he stop them?
卑职义乌县令赵大河
Generals, I'm Zhao Dahe,
拜见戚将军 卢将军
the county magistrate of Yiwu.
赵大人 这些村民为何打斗
Why are these people fighting?
二位有所不知呀
You don't understand.
义乌这地一向贫瘠
Yiwu has always been poor and barren.
可最近有老百姓发现了一些金矿
But the folks have discovered a gold mine lately
和一些金属的矿
along with other metal ores.
他们称这边为八宝山
People started calling this area Treasure Hill.
附近永康的村民一听说了 就来探矿
Villagers from Yongkang came to mine the ores
这不 两方面就打起来了
and the parties started to fight.
早些天还来过一次了
They came several days ago
已经被义乌的村民给打退了
and the villagers from Yiwu fought them off.
这两天不 又来第二次
But they keep coming back.
胡大人
Commander!
我在义乌发现了可练之兵
I found men in Yiwu I can train.
我正找你呢
Just the man I want.
自己好好看看吧
Take a look at this.
说我拉拢赵文华
It says here I kiss up to Zhao Wenhua,
靠权术取代张经大人
replaced Zhang Jing through political trickery
出谋献计把他害死
and eventually devised a ploy to murder him.
都是你元敬说的话吗
Did you say that?
若不是锦衣卫的弟兄们都被我收买了
If I didn't pay off the Imperial Secret Service
这话传到赵大人的耳中
and they managed to report this to Zhen Wenhua,
你早就和张经大人同一个下场了
you'd suffer the same fate as Zhang Jing.
我争官是真的
No doubt I was after his position,
但是杀死张经大人
but killing Zhang Jing
非我之意
was not my idea.
说我背弃道义
They say I was treacherous
诱劝王直投诚
and convinced Wang Zhi to surrender.
也非我所愿呀
That was not my idea either.
我何尝不想当一个
Don't you think I want to be
言而有信的大丈夫
a man of his word?
如果我真的能有掌控这一切
If only the situation was under my control,
那倭寇之患早就不战而退了
the pirates problem would be resolved without going to war.
元敬呀 元敬
Jiguang,
耳目众多呀
the walls have ears.
朝廷之事
With regards to the Imperial Court,
不是你随随便便就可以去谈论的
it's best you keep your opinions to yourself.
练兵打仗你是奇才
You're a genius in commanding and training your troops,
但是做官
but when it comes to politics,
你还真的好好学学
you have so much to learn.
听说你要换兵是吗
You want a new army?
这一笔钱呢
This money
本来是用作你官升一位的礼金
was supposed to buy you a promotion.
但是我猜 你肯定是想把这笔钱
But I guess you'd rather use it
用到义乌的练兵之用了
to train soldiers in Yiwu.
好了
Very well!
兵的事
I'll leave the Army
就交给你了
in your capable hands.
谢大人
Thank you, sir!
诸位义乌村民 听我说
Listen to me, folks.
我们这一次是来征兵打仗的 去打倭寇
We're recruiting soldiers to fight pirates.
我什么也不知道
I don't know.
反正大家去 我就去
You go, I go.
我给大家念念
Let me read this for you.
只要是臂膀腰…
With strong arms...
骗人的
Liar!
赵大河
Zhao Dahe,
你收了永康的人多少好处
how much did Yongkang village pay you
来骗我的人去当兵
to con us into joining the army
让人家来抢我们的矿
so they can steal our mines?
你胡说什么
Watch your mouth!
谁敢抛下义乌去当兵的
Whoever leaves Yiwu to join the Army
就是跟我结仇
is my enemy.
都听到没有
Hear that?
谁都不准去
No one is leaving.
听我再讲 跟大家聊一聊
Listen to me...
别紧张别紧张
Relax!
我们是找大成有事
We came to see Dacheng.
这边请
This way...
大成呀 大成
Dacheng“.
戚将军找你有要事相商呀
General Qi wants a word with you.
请
Please
走吧
Go away!
别再烦了
Leave me alone!
打仗是你们当兵的事
Going to war is your business.
这打倭寇是我们所有人的事呀
Fighting pirates is everyone's business.
大成兄
Dacheng,
没人愿意打仗呀
no one wants to go to war.
可是如果有人来侵犯咱们
In the face of an invasion,
咱们可得保护自己家园呀
we must fight to protect our homes.
这个道理你应该懂
You must know that.
我呸
Damn!
我们矿被抢的时候
When they came to rob us,
你们在哪
where were you?
男人说大事你懂什么呀
Don't butt in, this is man talk.
加水
More water.
对呀
She's right.
我们矿被抢的时候你们在哪
Where were you when they robbed us?
你们当兵的
As a soldier,
怎么不保护我们呢
why didn't you protect us?
我们在打倭寇
We were busy fighting pirates.
否则 来抢你们矿的就不是永康的村民
Or else villagers from Yongkang won't be robbing you.
而是倭寇了
It would be the pirates.
你们能抵挡得了吗
Can you fight them off?
如果你们愿意跟着我干
If you follow me,
我会派军队来保护你们的矿
I'll send the Army to protect your mines.
好奇怪呀你
You're funny!
本来就有兵
You already have an Army.
来找我干嘛
What do you want with us?
因为你们都是好汉
Because you are good men.
看你说话口甜舌滑的
You're such a smooth talker.
你是不是男人呀
Are you even a man?
看你蛮不讲理 你才不是男人
You're being unreasonable. You must not be a man.
大成
Dacheng,
我要给你讲什么道理 你才会答应我呢
what will it take for you to say yes?
拳头
Your fists.
我只懂拳头
That's all I know.
奉陪
I'm happy to oblige.
我拳头舒服吗
How do you like my fists?
你的手没事吧
How is your hand?
承让
Thank you, I won.
承让什么
Says who?
我还没输呢
I have not yet lost!
继续跑呀
Keep running!
过来帮忙 救人呀
Give me a hand!
好了 不用送了
No need to walk us out.
过几天我带他们过去
I'll bring them to you in a few days.
好
Great!
你答应的事要做到
You must keep your word.
当然
Of course!
如果有人敢来抢你们的矿
If anyone tries to steal your mines,
我戚继光第一个来护着
I'll be the first to protect them.
大成 你大可放心
Don't worry, Dacheng.
这戚将军可是一言九鼎呀
General Qi is a man of his word.
戚将军
General Qi,
果然英明
you're so brilliant.
这真是两全其美的好方案吶
This is a win-win solution.
你也跟我们一起去
You should come with us.
我们上战场
We're going onto the battlefield;
你怎么在这里舒服的当官呀
you shouldn't be here doing a cushy job.
就是呀 你得去呀
That's right. You must come with us.
这 赵某人可是文人
I'm a scholar.
在战场上打打杀杀
I have no business
不是我的事呀
fighting in the battlefield.
打倭寇是大家的事呀
Fighting pirates is everyone's business.
你说的呀
You said that yourself.
去呀去不去呀
Are you coming or not?
赵大人
Magistrate,
您最了解义乌的民情了
nobody knows Yiwu better than you.
如果有您出面当我们的军监
You're best suited
是最合适不过的
to be the Army prefect.
好
Great!
只要你们愿意随..  随戚将军去当军
If you're willing to follow General Qi,
我赵某人
I, Zhao Dahe,
愿舍命相陪
am willing to risk my life
舍命相陪
and go wherever you go!
好
Good!
接下来会为大家讲解地图
Let me explain the map to you.
来看看你训练的新军
I came to see your new Army.
这就是你们的家义乌
This is your home, Yiwu.
我们这里是新河
We're in Xinhe.
为什么义乌怎么这么小
Why is Yiwu so small?
地图嘛
It's only a map.
小心 小心
Be careful...
干嘛 看看
Look!
这个东西叫做狼筅
This bamboo spear is called Wolf Brush.
不懂了吧
You don't understand?
把那个给我
Pass me that...
这使用的时候
When you use this,
我们要把它架着
insert the branches and leaves.
这次你们再看看
Look again.
看起来好奇怪
Looks weird, right?
停
Stop!
大家等一下
Let's wait!
大家原地休息
Take a break on the spot.
当兵还要整天跑步的
Why do we have to run?
行军呀 没气行什么军
You need strength.
怎么打
How else can you fight?
我以前没感觉那么累
I have never been this tired before.
楼将军
General Lou!
我和大家一起去训练
I've been practicing with you.
我能够有一套军服吗
Can I have an army uniform?
小鬼 你可别忘了
Don't forget
你可是胡大人的人啊
you work for Commander Hu.
我们哪敢送你
We wouldn't dare give it to you.
还可以吗
Can you manage?
行
Yes.
继续
Carry on!
只要你不放弃
If you won't give up,
我们就不放弃你
we won't give up on you.
好
Good!
继续
Carry on!
万众一心兮
If we stand united,
群山可撼
we can bring down the mountains.
惟忠与义兮
If we are loyal and patriotic,
气冲斗牛
we can ward off all obstacles.
主将亲我兮
The General cares about us
胜如父母
like our parents.
干犯军法兮
If we break the rules,
身不自由
we shall be punished.
号令明兮
If we obey direct orders,
赏罚信
reward and punishment shall be fair.
赴水火兮
We go through fire and water
敢迟留
without hesitation.
上报天子兮
We serve His Majesty
下救黔首
and save the people.
杀尽倭奴兮
Kill pirates
觅个封侯
and seek titles.
举刀
Raise your sabers!
收
Back!
万众一心兮
If we stand united,
群山可撼
we can bring down the mountains.
惟忠与义兮
If we are loyal and patriotic,
气冲斗牛
we can ward off all obstacles.
主将亲我兮
The General cares about us
胜如父母
like our parents
干犯军法兮
If we break the rules,
身不自由
we shall be punished
我回来了
I'm home!
哥
Jiguang!
真是抱歉了
I'm so sorry.
刚才我去拜访唐顺之唐大人
I was visiting with Minister Tang Shunzhi.
聊得一时兴起就忘了时间了
We had a nice visit and forgot the time.
这是唐大人送给我的
This is a gift from him.
哥
Jiguang,
我们先吃饭吧
let's eat.
你们一直在等我呀
You've been waiting for me?
没事 没事
It's quite alright.
等等无妨的
We don't mind waiting.
抱歉
I'm sorry.
来 吃饭
Let's eat.
我来
I'll take that.
来来来吃饭
Come on, let's eat.
夫人
My dear,
这些书可是唐大人一生的心血
these books are Minister Tang's life's work.
夫人 来
Come on...
夫人
My dear...
不行
No!
这些菜都凉了
The food is cold.
小牟
Xiao Mou,
把菜都撤了
clear the table.
对不起诸位了
I'm sorry, gentlemen.
你们出去吃吧
Please eat out.
夫人
My dear...
不就回来晚了一点嘛
I'm just a little late for dinner.
没必要把事情闹大吧
There's no need to make such a fuss.
我闹了吗
Did I?
戚将军家宴客
General Qi is entertaining at home.
就不该待慢客人
We must not be rude.
你是在跟我发脾气吗
Are you picking a fight?
夫人
Stop it!
先告退了
We should go.
消消气我哥不好 他不好
It's his fault.
先走了
I better leave.
我跟你们说
Listen to me,
以后戚将军的事情
from now on, General Qi's business
就是我们大家的事情啊
is our business.
女人呀
Women!
是要挫她一下威风
You must put her in her place.
你要告诉她谁才是一家之主
Let her know who's in charge.
你要告诉她
You must tell her.
你心狠了
Be tough.
忍无可忍
Don't take it anymore.
老虎
Even a tiger
也有睡觉的时候呀
will fall asleep.
你待她睡觉了
When she's asleep,
拿把刀 架她脖子上
put a knife to her neck.
叫她起来 然后再告诉她
Wake her up and tell her
你要是还不服的话
if she refuses to obey,
大不了先杀了你再自尽
you'll kill her.
以振夫纲
You must subjugate her.
好
Yes!
大成说得好 这话说真对
Hear, hear! Dacheng is right!
哥我们就这么办
That's what we should do.
夫人
My dear...
为什么拿着剑
What are you doing with the sword?
我想杀只鸡给夫人补补身子
I want to kill a chicken for you as a tonic.
你的剑怎么用来杀鸡呢
Your sword should not be used to kill a chicken.
大成
Dacheng,
谁请夫人过来的
who invited my wife?
将军不敢自己出手
We know you couldn't do it.
我们兄弟们愿意为你出手
We decided to do it for you.
等一会掷杯为号
Drop the cup as our signal,
我们几个人一起用刀架她
we'll hold her at knife point.
你什么都不用多说
You don't need to say anything.
我们来说就好
We'll do the talking for you.
没事的 你放心
Don't worry. Everything will be fine.
夫人来了来了来了
Here she comes...
相公
Jiguang,
有什么要紧的事呀
what's so urgent
非得叫我现在过来
that I must come over right away?
戚夫人
Madam Qi.
奉茶
Serve tea.
嫂子
Sister.
怎么了你们
What's wrong?
为什么都怪怪的
You're all acting weird.
戚将军
General Qi!
茶
Your tea...
到底出什么事了
What's going on?
夫人
My dear,
想请你看看我们练兵的状况
I want you to watch our training
给点意见
and give us some advice.
我哪懂这些
I don't know anything about that.
就阅兵
Just review the troops.
阅兵
Review the troops.
阅兵好
Good idea!
我去准备
I'll go get ready.
听到了
You heard him.
阅兵
Review the troops.
走了
Let's go.
戚将军是个好榜样呀
General Qi set a good example.
等等
Wait!
不是这你也在记下来呀
Don't write that down!
这是史 历史呀
It's part of history.
什么史 你给我撕了
What history? Tear that up!
木幡的狼人部队已出发到宁海了
Kohata's ronins already set out for Ninghai.
才三千一百三十四人
They have 3,134 men.
戚继光的军队不管多精良
Regardless of how effective Qi's troops are,
将军也不用这样忧心吧
there's no need for you to worry.
听说要当他兵的人
I heard he set strict criteria for his recruits.
大城里生活的不收 当过官的不收
No one from the big city or has been in office.
皮肤白的不收 胆子小的不行
No one with fair complexion, no cowards.
胆子大又不可以
Nobody too daring either.
这样子
Just imagine,
这些是什么人呀
what kind of people would he end up with?
就是笨的人呀
Fools!
不笨的不敢带呢
He'll end up commanding fools.
岑港之战
At the battle of Cengang,
我们是能够完全打败他们
we have the ability to defeat them.
但老师却不让我们继续应战
But Sensei won't let us engage them.
如果那个时候我们继续应战
Had we done that back then,
我们今天根本就不用担心戚继光
we wouldn't have to worry about Qi today.
少主你是在批评我吗
Are you criticizing me?
我不明白
I don't understand.
我们结集了两万大军
We have 20,000 men.
只要直接进攻台州
If we attack Taizhou directly,
到时候戚继光一定跟我们对战
Qi will have to engage us
然后把他击败就可以了
and we can defeat him.
如今却兵分三路
Why split the Army three ways?
同时攻击宁海台州又有什么意义呢
What's the use of attacking Ninghai and Taizhou simultaneously?
意义是在于必胜
To ensure a sure win.
派浪人部队到宁海
Sending the ronins to Ninghai
是要让戚继光的兵走一天的路去迎战
will make Qi's troops travel one day to fight.
而我们在他迎击浪人的时候 进攻台州
We take Taizhou while they're engaged with the ronins.
那新河呢
What about Xinhe?
攻一个空的军营又是为什么
What's the point of attacking an empty barrack?
戚继光和他军队的家人 都在新河呀
Qi and his troops' families are in Xinhe.
保护战地
Between defending the land
还是保护家人
and protecting their families,
你说他们会选哪一个
how would they choose?
无论他怎样选择
Whatever they choose to do,
都会是个很有趣的局面
it'll be a very interesting situation.
我们就在这里等他上钩
We'll wait for them to take the bait.
过去倭寇来犯从来没有超过三千人
Pirates never brought more than 3,000 men.
而这次
But this time,
在奉化附近登岸的
20,000 pirates
倭寇近有两万之众
landed near Fenghua.
元敬
Jiguang,
你的新兵只有三千
your new Army only has 3,000 men.
怎么去迎战
How can you fight them?
胡大人
Commander,
你这是送羊入虎口
you are sending sheep to a tiger.
卢大人
General Lu,
我们可不是羊吶
we're not sheep.
你别逞强
Don't get in over your head.
那还要再等多长时间呀
How much longer must we wait?
多等一天
The longer we wait,
老百姓就要多受一天的苦
the longer our people will suffer.
绝对不能让贼倭再深入下去了
We must stop the pirates' threat.
其他同僚
Does anyone else
真的没有一点对策了吗
have any counter measures?
倭兵在宁海集结不动
Japanese soldiers congregated in Ninghai but made no moves
就是要引你上钩呀
because they want you to take the bait.
我愿意上这个钩
I'm willing to take the bait.
如果我不上钩 对方就不会动
If I don't, they won't make a move.
上次岑港之战我们知道
The battle of Cengang tells us
对方有个懂兵法的人在调度
they have military strategists among them.
这次很可能是同一批人
It's probably the same group.
我建议
I suggest
台州 象山的兵马按兵不动
troops in Taizhou and Xiangshan should lay low
以防他们乘虚而入
to ensure the pirates can't take advantage of our weak defense.
我愿意率领新军先打头阵
I'll take the lead with the new Army.
等探明对方的意图之后
When we find out their real motive,
再请大人定夺
we'll let Commander Hu make a ruling.
这次
This time,
绝对不能让他们再跑了
we won't let them get away again.
好
Good!
元敬
Jiguang,
马上领军到宁海
set out for Ninghai right away.
卢将军
General Lu,
你呢 随我到台州坐镇
we'll take command of Taizhou.
其余部队
The rest of the troops
原地待命 加强防守
will stay put and beef up defense
听候指令
pending our new order.
大人英明
Good idea, Commander!
Good idea!
不用你们打就是英明了 啊
Because you're not doing the fighting.
就这么决定了
So be it.
听说
I heard
对方来了两万兵
the enemy has 20,000 men.
别挂念
Don't worry!
谢谢夫人
Thank you.
两万
20,000 men.
两万的倭寇
20,000 pirates.
这仗能打得赢吗
Can we beat them?
上次我们两万人打了一千倭寇
Last time we outnumbered them 20,000 to 1,000
打了半年都没打完
and the war dragged on for 6 months.
等等吧
Just wait.
这帮人还不知道自己要去送死吗
Don't they know they're on a suicide mission?
还威风呢
And they look so confident.
说什么了
What did you say?
有本事你去呀
I'd like to see you take their place.
你们天天个个胆小鬼一样在这里耗着
You're a bunch of cowards hanging out here.
有本事上战场
Why don't you go to the frontline?
有什么权利说别人
You have no right to criticize.
筷子
Chopsticks!
胆小鬼
Cowards!
爹
Father!
慢点慢点
Slow down...
爹很快回来
We have to leave.
好走
Go...
头
Chief!
他们不会要我们去送死吧
Are they sending us on a suicide mission?
你这么怕死呀
Are you afraid to die?
怎么可能有这种事
How is this possible?
明军可以厉害到什么地步啊
How formidable is the Ming Army?
我们现在是最大的威胁
We're their biggest threat.
不过
But...
我担心的是
I'm more worried
他们一看见我们的身影
when they get a glimpse of us,
卷着尾巴就逃跑了
they'll run with their tails between their legs.
哎呀
Oh
我缺女人呀
I need women.
想起都觉得兴奋
The thought of them makes me excited.
明军快来
The Ming Army is coming!
快快打完我便去宁海找美女
Finish them off and I'll get a woman in Ninghai.
说的对
Absolutely!
傻瓜 女人和钱
If you want women and money,
当然都去台州
go to Taizhou.
台州才是大城
They have things that can satisfy us.
我缺钱呀
I need money.
打完这一仗赶紧向大人要报酬吧
Ask for our reward after this.
想回家了
I want to go home.
头
Chief!
明军就在前面了
The Ming Army is up ahead.
来送死的
They came here to die.
去吧
Go!
头来来来
Come on, Chief...
做个将军的样子
act like a general.
将军
General?
这么好
This is great!
出阵
Let's go!
不是说有两万的吗
Didn't they say 20,000 men?
先别想那么多
Never mind that.
命令大家从两翼展开
Tell the others to split up.
小心有埋伏
Watch out for ambush.
是
Aye!
听着
Listen up!
两边列阵
Split up the formation.
等等！
Wait!
准备枪
Rifles!
开枪
Fire!
冲呀
Charge!
停呀
Stop!
挡
Block!
长枪
Spears!
拖走
Drag them away!
三眼铳
Three-eyed hand cannons!
蹲
Get down!
开火
Fire!
发生什么事
What's going on?
退吧 退吧
Fall back!
退吧…
Back up...
"Over 300 pirates died while only a few Ming soldiers were injured."
哥
Jiguang!
胡大人派兵来报
A message from Commander Hu.
新河附近发现倭兵
Japanese soldiers in Xinhe!
大成哥
Dacheng!
倭兵攻打我们家了
Japanese soldiers attacked our homes.
什么 你说什么
What did you say?
攻打我们家了 倭兵
Japanese soldiers attacked our homes.
大哥 怎么办
What should we do?
戚将军
General Qi,
倭寇攻打到新河了
the pirates went after Xinhe.
我们赶快回去吧
Let's hurry back.
对呀我们赶快回去吧
That's right! Let's go!
回去吧
Let's go back!
大家可别给倭寇骗了
Don't let them fool you.
他们大老远来
You think they came all this way
难道只为了新河吗
to take Xinhe?
新河
Xinhe
那里有我们的亲人呀
is where our families are.
对呀是呀 亲人都在那儿呢
Yes, our families are there.
来来来 过来
Come over here...
过来看看
Look!
大家看
Take a look,
一队在宁海出现
Ningha...
一队在新河出现
Xinhe...
为什么
Why?
为了就是掩饰他们的目标
To cover up their real target.
台州
Taizhou.
台州可是城府
Taizhou is the provincial capital.
对倭寇来讲
To the pirates,
那里才大有价值
it's worth a lot more.
哥
Jiguang,
可是嫂子在新河
your wife is there.
就是因为她在我才不担心
She's precisely the reason I'm not worried.
新河现在驻军就剩两百人
Only 200 men are stationed in Xinhe.
怎么行
That's not enough.
两百足够了
That's quite enough.
别忘了
Don't forget,
我夫人可是天下无敌啊
my wife is invincible.
要不这样
How about...
楼楠
Lou Nan!
你带领一半兵马先赶回去救援
Take half the troops with you back to Xinhe.
之后再赶回台州跟我们会合
Then meet us in Taizhou.
大成哥
Dacheng,
都说保家卫国
we should protect our homes and defend our state.
家都保不了 谈什么卫国
But without a home, who cares about the state?
闭嘴
Shut up!
戚将军都不担心
If General Qi is not worried,
你们担心什么呀
why should you be?
去
Go!
我们准备出发
Get ready to leave.
大成哥
Dacheng“.
去啊
Go!
走
Come on...
将军
General,
我军只有三千兵
we only have 3,000 men.
现在还一分为二
If we split the troops in half,
倭军人马两万呀
can we take on
可行吗
20,000 Japanese soldiers?
不行也得行
We'll have to.
台州不能失
We can't lose Taizhou.
大家的家眷可都托付给你了
Our families are in your good hands.
哥
Jiguang,
我们先去新河再去台州 也赶得及
we can still make Taizhou in time after Xinhe.
闭嘴
Shut up!
你再多说一个字
Another word out of you,
我先斩你
I'll have you beheaded.
好
Very well.
将军
General,
你放心
rest assured
如果新河有什么闪失
if anything happens to Xinhe,
我楼楠
Lou Nan
不会活着回来见你
will not come back alive.
拜托了
Thank you.
来 把东西全都装起来
Pack up everything.
能拿走的东西快拿走
Take whatever we can.
动作快点
On the double...
快 走
Go...
戚夫人
Madam Qi,
我怎么就跟你说不明白了
why can't you understand?
这上万的倭兵马上要到新河城了
Over 10,000 Japanese soldiers will be in Xinhe soon.
我们已经派人去找戚将军去了
I already sent a message to General Qi.
你现在听我的赶紧收拾精致细软
Listen to me and pack your things.
卑职送你出城
I'll escort you out of town.
我们出城那新河怎么办
Then what will happen to Xinhe?
黄岩的乡兵
Village soldiers are
和太平的乡兵现在就在城外抵抗
fighting outside the city right now.
这整个县衙之内
We have less than
新河城之内就不到两百个衙役呀
200 soldiers in Xinhe,
- 能顶得…  - 戚夫人
- how can... - Madam Qi!
他们说倭寇来了
They say the pirates are coming.
我们该怎么办
What should we do?
你看你看
See?
马上找人敲钟 召集全城老百姓
Sound the bell and summon everyone in town.
走 赶紧
Let's go!
小牟去把盔甲拿来
Xiao Mou, bring my armor.
你们要干什么
What are you doing?
走走走赶紧
Hurry up...
这以为做假装的
You think this is a game?
这是打仗要死人吶
We're going to war. People may die.
倭寇你见过嘛 我见过
Have you seen a pirate? I have.
我杀过
I killed some of them.
再不走就来不及了
Time is running out.
我是戚将军夫人
I am General Qi's wife.
我没有办法扔下新河的老百姓自己逃命
I cannot run away and abandon the people of Xinhe.
你若想走
If you want to leave,
请自便
go ahead.
我怎么就跟她说不明白了
Why can't I reason with her?
走走走
Let's go.
别走别走
Don't go!
跑了也没有用
What's the use of running?
还不如跟他们拼了吶
Might as well stay and fight.
来来来
Come on...
戚夫人带人来拿兵器了
Madam Qi came to get weapons.
不是说好了那有人把守的吗
Didn't we agree someone will guard the city?
都给打晕了
They were knocked out cold.
夫人 你等一下
Wait up, Madam!
让开
Step aside!
你们别走了
Don%leave!
你们别走呀
大娘来 喝喝水吧
Auntie, drink some water.
当心自己
Be careful!
大爷喝喝水
Here, drink some water.
夫人
Madam,
戚将军 能赶回来吗
will General Qi be back in time?
他会回来的
Yes, he will.
那就好
That's good.
大家都放心吧
Don't worry, folks.
戚将军一定会赶回来的
General Qi will be back.
好好好
Very well.
我们拼了老命也守住
We'll guard the city with our lives.
杨大哥
Brother Yang,
你们怎么回来了
what are you doing here?
你们不怕死吗
You're not afraid to die?
怕死
Am.
只是夫人不走
But if you're staying,
我们又怎么能走呢
how can we leave
让后辈子孙笑呀
and become the laughing stock?
你
You...
大哥
Brother...
去教他们三眼铳
Teach them how to use the hand cannons.
来兄弟们
Come on...
夫人
Madam,
守城 是我的责任
it's my duty to guard the city.
交给我吧
Leave that to me.
后面跟上
Keep UP...
快
Hurry!
将士们坚持
Keep it UP...
我们一定要坚持 快
We shall prevail! Hurry!
我们深夜才行动
Wait till midnight to make our move.
是
Aye!
跑 都给我加快
Run! Hurry up!
跑
Run!
头他们更起劲了
Chief, they seem quite energetic.
就让戚继光多活几个时辰吧
Let Qi live a few more hours.
自己部队中计都不知
He doesn't know he's walking into a trap.
戚继光和老狐狸互打的时候
When he takes on the sly old fox,
我们在后面伏击
we'll ambush them from behind.
妙计
Brilliant!
报告戚将军
General,
一股倭兵在城府四里外花街镇札营
the Japanese soldiers encamped in Huajie, 4 miles outside the city.
城府中 胡大人和三千官兵已做好布防
Commander Hu and 3,000 men have already set up defense in the city.
果然是台州
They're after Taizhou after all.
敌军人数是多少
How many men do they have?
他们大概有八千到一万左右
Between 8,000 to 10,000.
继美 军旗
Jimei! Banner!
是
Aye!
哥
Here!
把我的军旗交给台州城府的胡大人
Give this to Commander Hu.
请他们挂起来
Ask him to hoist it.
就说我马上回来取
Tell him I'll be back for it.
遵命
Aye!
走
Let's go!
宁海的浪人部队已经被他打败
If ronins defeated him in Ninghai.
那我便让浪人去进攻台州
I'll let the ronins attack Taizhou
我们的部队依然发毫不损
and our troops won't suffer any casualties.
这太让人气馁了
That is so discouraging.
只要除掉戚继光
Once we get rid of Qi,
让明国放弃了建立强大军队的决心
Ming won't be so determined to build a strong army
我们就可以胜利
and we'll have a chance to win.
大人
Sir,
戚继光的军队出现在花街
Qi's troops showed up on Hua Street.
有人跌入圈套了
Someone is about to fall into a trap.
这就是新的明军呀
This is the new Army?
这样的阵型
What kind of formation is this?
那是什么兵器
Look at those weapons.
我没见过
I have never seen that before.
你也没见过
You haven't either?
通知小田副将的部队 加入包围明军
Tell Oda and his troops to encircle the Ming troops.
还有
Also...
准备一些长竹竿对付他们的盾
find long bamboo poles to tackle their shields.
是
Aye!
三眼铳 发射
Three-eyed hand cannons! Fire!
退后
Fall back!
给我追
After them!
大成跟上
Dacheng, follow them.
给我跟上 来跟上
Move it! Keep up!
虎蹲炮跟上 你殿后
Bring up the rear!
好
Aye!
快
Hurry!
大家往后退
Back up...
后面的盾阵快过来帮忙 给我顶住
Bring the shields forward!
狼筅
Wolf Brushes!
狼筅不够长
They're not long enough!
挺住
Hold them off!
退
Fall back!
中计了
They fell for it.
真的中计了
They're trapped.
头 现在有什么行动
Chief, what do we do now?
去找老狐狸
Let's go find the old fox.
小心
Watch out!
开
Open!
走
Go!
大成
Dacheng!
将军
General!
他们的主将就在东北角
Their commander is at the northeast corner.
让大家分散
Split up
进入小巷
and go through the alleys.
在东北角汇合
I'll meet you at the northeast corner.
谁发现他们的主将便发候箭
Whoever finds the commander should fire the signal arrow.
你跟我走
You come with me.
来 跟着我 分散
Follow me. Split up.
冲
Charge!
快 快 掩护
Hurry...cover up for us!
快
Hurry!
大人
Sir!
戚继光的部队
Qi's troops are
正自小巷向我们本阵方向进发
moving towards us through the alleys.
什么？戚继光吗
Qi?
我们慎重的迎接他吧
Let's give him a warm welcome.
要让他们回到大街
Drive them back to the main street
我们才可以围剿他们
so we can encircle them and take them out.
可怜的戚继光啊
Poor Qi.
老师
Sensei,
我们的铁炮队
our Guns Unit
不应又在后卫吧
should not remain in the rear.
你跟木幡的浪人部队守着后阵
Guard the back of our camp with Kohata and the ronins.
你别小看你的作用
Don't underestimate your task.
出发
Just do it.
去吧
Let's go!
杀呀
Come on.
冲呀
Charge!
大成 你的腿怎么了
Dacheng, how is your leg?
我没事
I'm fine.
你给我回去
Go back
带着虎蹲炮
and bring the Crouching Tiger Cannon.
你要跟上 去呀
You must keep up. Go!
你保重呀
Take care!
这边
This way.
报告
Sir!
在洗衣坊附近发现一队明军
Ming troops were discovered near Xiyi Lane.
报告
Sir!
木下部队在市场街道和明军作战中
Kinoshita's men are fighting Ming troops on the streets of the market.
还有在祠堂附近发现明军
We also found Ming troops near the shrine.
全力堵住他们
Try your best to cut them off
彻底的消灭他们
and take them out completely.
是
Aye!
报告
Sir!
明军快到附近了
The Ming troops are approaching.
找到主将 大家准备
We found their commander, get ready!
长竹竿 列阵
Bamboo pole formation!
准备
Ready!
杀
Charge!
盾牌
Shields!
人家在立功
Others are contributing,
我们却在这里吹着风
while we're here shooting the breeze.
少主
Master Yamagawa,
虽然我不太清楚
maybe I don't understand,
但你不是应该才是主将吗
but I thought you were the commander.
为什么
Why?
为什么我们不去头阵打
Why aren't we spearheading this campaign?
如果是我们铁炮队打头阵的话
If we send in the Guns Unit,
一定能阻止戚继光前进
we can stop Qi's advances.
那老狐狸 怕少主你有什么事
The old fox is worried if anything should happen to you,
回去会被主公怪责吧
your father may blame him.
但你不同
But it's different for you.
什么人也能瞬间把他打倒
Anyone can topple him in an instant.
只要你的铁炮队跟我联手
If your Guns Unit join forces with me,
不管是谁
no matter who it is,
我们都能瞬间打倒
we can instantly take them out.
我为报一战之仇
I want revenge,
你为建功成名去冲吧
while you want a reputation.
我啊
Me?
我也想成为真正的武士
I want to be a genuine samurai.
要当真正的武士
To be a samurai,
你别再奸淫掳掠了
you must stop your plundering and rape.
我当然知道
Of course I know that.
还有
Also,
我被你直话直说的性格感染了
I like your straight talk.
去吧
Let's do it.
好
Good!
拿酒来
Bring us wine!
一起来
Come on!
他们看像守着作战
They're guarding more than they are fighting.
被动攻击是他想出来的吗
He invented this passive attack?
他们都是人
They're humans after all.
等太久会累的
Waiting too long will wear them out.
看他们还能等多久
They can't wait much longer.
别焦急继续不停攻击
Be patient and carry on with the attack.
如果找到突破位就攻进去吧
Make headway if you can find a breach.
是
Aye!
大家太累了 冲不过去
We're exhausted. We can't break through.
虎蹲炮呢
Where are the Crouching Tiger Cannons?
未追上
They can't keep up.
顶住
Hold them off!
不要后退
Don't back off.
往前冲
Charge forward!
怎么不通
We can't get through.
前面给堵住了
The road ahead is blocked.
冲不出去呀
We can't get through.
来这边 快
Come this way. Hurry!
你能不能准一点
Can you aim better?
在打仗呀
We're at war!
方向就对了
This is the right direction.
往回走
Go back!
你拿着个破罗盘有什么用
Your broken compass is useless.
小心
Watch out!
盾牌
Shields!
三眼铳
Three-eyed hand cannons!
小鬼
Kid!
小鬼你怎么啦
What's wrong with you, kid?
你醒醒呀小鬼
Wake up, kid!
别跟我开玩笑小鬼
This is not funny, kid!
你醒醒呀小鬼
Wake up, kid!
小鬼
Kid!
你醒醒呀
Wake up!
小鬼你醒醒呀 我给你军服
Wake up, kid! I'll give you a uniform.
这是在搞什么鬼呀
What the hell is this?
我想少主只是想替你速战速决呢
He wants to help you wrap this up quickly.
可拜托你替他守住后卫吗
Can you guard the back in his place?
没问题
No problem!
跟我来
Follow me!
铁炮队
Guns Unit!
准备
Ready!
瞄准
Aim...
一起 开
fire!
让开
Make Way!
散开
Break it up!
- 让开  - 散开
- Make way!  - Break it up!
他妈的 闪开
Damn it! Dodge!
少主
Master Yamagawa!
他们一千多兵大败近两万倭寇
Defeating 20,000 pirates with only 1,000 men
真是不容易呀
has not been easy.
这代价 不少呀
A high price to pay.
戚将军呢
Where is General Qi?
戚将军领兵继续追剿倭寇
He went after the pirates.
那是倭兵的主力
They are the leaders of the pirates.
不能让他们给跑了
We can't let them get away.
元敬呀元敬
Jiguang,
你是抛下新河的家眷都不顾了
you abandoned your family in Xinhe.
卢将军
General Lu!
在
Yes?
快
Hurry...
快派人去支援新河
Send back up to Xinhe.
只希望
Let's hope
新河能守得住
Xinhe is still defensible.
遵命
Aye!
跟我来
Follow me.
三眼铳准备好就可以上了
Bring the Three-eyed hand cannons when they're ready.
不要让他们靠近城门
Keep them off the city gate!
夫人
Madam!
是个美女呀
A pretty lady!
去死吧
You're dead!
夫人
Madam!
夫人 你没事吧
Are you alright, Madam?
冲呀
Charge!
小牟
Xiao Mou!
走
Come on!
冲呀
Charge!
攻城
Break down the city gate!
小牟
Xiao Mou!
下去把城门堵住
Go block the city gate.
你俩快去帮小牟 快
You two give Xiao Mou a hand. Hurry!
快 换火药
Hurry, load the gunpowder.
不要让他们靠近城门
Keep them off the city gate!
退后
Fall back!
大家一起扛
Help carry this...
快点 堵住城门
Hurry, block the city gate!
第二队
Team 2!
上
Move!
攻呀
Charge!
抓住敌方大将
Seize the commander!
冲呀
Charge!
把门爆开
Blow up the gate!
再冲
Charge!
攻呀
兄弟们 上
Charge!
插
Attack!
冲
Charge!
大哥
Brother Yang!
夫人
Madam!
城守住了嘛
The city is safe!
守住了
We did it.
戚将军回来了
General Qi is back!
城守住了
The city is safe!
还好
Good!
我没有给戚将军丢脸
I did not embarrass General Qi.
大哥
Brother Yang!
后面的兄弟还没有跟上
The others can't keep up.
要不要等他们
Shall we wait?
明军呀 他们追上来了
The Ming troops are catching up.
别怕 快上船
Don't worry, get on board.
他们过不了泥滩的
They couldn't get across the mudflats.
你们看 那是什么
Look! What is that?
走吧 走吧
Let's go...
退呀 快点退
Fall back... hurry!
快点 快点上船
Hurry! Get on board!
快
Go!
Hurry!
快点上船
Get on board!
快点
Hurry!
关上门
Close the door.
快点上船
Get on board!
快点
Hurry!
快点 快点上船
Hurry! They're catching up!
快点 要开船了
Hurry, we have to set sail.
大船赶不及了
We can't make it to the vessel.
大家上小船 上啊
Board the small ship.
一 二 拉
One... two... pull!
已准备好可以上船了
Get ready to board!
一起上吧
Let's go together.
少主
Master Yamagawa!
这是我给你最后一个命令
This is my final order to you.
上船
Get on board.
一起吧
Let's go together.
老师
Sense
我错了
I was wrong.
现在
Now,
我终于明白老师为什么一直谨慎
I finally understand why you have been prudent.
以后
From now on,
我不会再自大了
I won't be arrogant anymore.
老师
Sensei
请跟我们一起走吧
Come with us.
学到就好了
I'm glad you learned your lesson.
两万军队如今只剩几百
We only have several hundred men left from 20,000.
一直指挥大家退却的将军 这次不能退了
I can't go home like this.
你替我告诉主公
Tell my Lord
明军已经建起来了
The Matsura clan
我们松蒲藩再不要妄想了
should stop dreaming.
快
Hurry!
快上船
Get on board!
少主
Master Yamagawa!
少主 我们要走吧
We must go.
老师
Sensei
- 老师  - 少主上船吧
- Sensei!  - Get on board!
少主去吧
Go!
少主
Master Yamagawa!
安心上船
Go home safely.
少主
Master Yamagawa!
戚继光是怎么让明军脱胎换骨的呀
The Ming Army is reborn under Qi's command.
明军人心变了
That's what I want to know.
变得强大了
They became stronger.
这是戚继光的厉害之处
That's the amazing thing about Qi.
让他人相信自己变强大了
He made them believe they could become stronger.
故兵无常势
The strength of an Army will change
水无常形
just like water will change its form.
能因敌变化而取胜者谓之神
He who can prevail in chaos is regarded as a god.
戚将军说过不能杀降兵
General Qi said prisoners of war must be spared.
不要管我
Leave me alone.
这是将令 将令啊
This is an order!
请
Please!
跑得很快呀
You're a fast runner.
我们接受投降
We accept your surrender.
可以知道你的名字吗
May I know your name?
名字不重要
The name is not important.
我就是倭寇
Iam a pirate.
来呀
Come on!
继美
Jimei!
戚继光
Qi Jiguang!